Guide to the Lindbergh Picture Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lindbergh picture collection
1840-1983
MS 325B
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
73.75
(102 boxes)
The collection consists of photographic prints, negatives, art prints, drawings, paintings, silhouettes, postcards, and motion picture film created or collected by Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh. The collection primarily documents the life and interests of Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, including childhoods, aviation and writing careers, expeditions and travels, and families. The bulk of the pictures document Charles Augustus Lindbergh's career in aviation, including his airmail service, barnstorming, historic solo transatlantic flight in the Spirit of St. Louis, and post flight interest in him by the media. The collection also provides researchers some of the earliest aerial views of the Southwest United States, Mexico and Latin America, Canada, Japan, China, and North Atlantic regions taken by the Lindberghs during their scientific aerial explorations and travels; documentation of the aviation industry including pioneers, early airplanes, air fields, and the use of aviation in the military, particularly during World War II. Additional photographs depict various immediate and extended Lindbergh, Land, Lodge, and Morrow relations as well as friends and acquaintances.
Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974
Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Photographs in box 102 are restricted pending preservation treatment and reformatting.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in eight series: Series I. Charles Augustus Lindbergh, 1902-1974. Series II. Anne Morrow Lindbergh, circa 1906-1977. Series III. Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh family, 1930-circa 1979. Series IV. Lindbergh/Land/Lodge families, circa 1940-1978. Series V. Morrow/Cutter family, circa 1873-1979. Series VI. Friends, acquaintances, and others, circa 1870-1979. Series VII. Topical, 1880-1983, undated. Series VIII. Graphic art and postcards, 1893-circa 1970s; IX. Motion picture film, Circa 1932-1962; and Oversize.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photographic prints, negatives, art prints, drawings, paintings, silhouettes, postcards, and motion picture film created or collected by Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh. The collection primarily documents the life and interests of Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, including childhoods, aviation and writing careers, expeditions and travels, and families. The bulk of the pictures document Charles Augustus Lindbergh's career in aviation, including his airmail service, barnstorming, historic solo transatlantic flight in the Spirit of St. Louis, and post flight interest in him by the media. The collection also provides researchers some of the earliest aerial views of the Southwest United States, Mexico and Latin America, Canada, Japan, China, and North Atlantic regions taken by the Lindberghs during their scientific aerial explorations and travels; documentation of the aviation industry including pioneers, early airplanes, air fields, and the use of aviation in the military, particularly during World War II. Additional photographs depict various immediate and extended Lindbergh, Land, Lodge, and Morrow relations as well as friends and acquaintances.
The collection includes pictures from various sources. In addition to photographs taken by or for Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, the collection includes photographs and art work handed down through their families, copies of photographs from the press and from libraries and archive collections, as well as photographs and artwork sent to the Lindberghs by members of the public. Due to the difficulty of identifying negatives and the existence of multiple copies, there is some duplication across series and folders.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles Augustus Lindbergh and his estate; and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, 1941-1988; gift of Hugo Visconti, 1999.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of the photographic images in the collection have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database (MADID).
Biographical / Historical
Charles Augustus Lindbergh (1902 Feb 4 -1974 Aug 26), aviator, author, biologist, and engineer, was the son of Charles August Lindbergh, a lawyer and congressman, and Evangeline Lodge Land, a science teacher whose father was Dr. Charles Land, a dentist and inventor. Born in Detroit, Lindbergh grew up in Little Falls, Minnesota, and Washington, DC. After studying engineering at the University of Wisconsin for three semesters he left in1922 to become an airplane pilot and barnstormer. In 1925 he graduated first in his class from the United States Army Air Service Flying School and became chief pilot of the new airmail line from St. Louis to Chicago.
On May 21, 1927, Lindbergh completed the first non-stop transatlantic flight from New York to Paris and was awarded the first Distinguished Flying Cross and the Congressional Medal of Honor. This feat, followed by the publication of his best-selling book We, great public receptions in Washington and New York, and an air tour making eighty-two stops in forty-eight states followed by one to Latin America in 1927-1928, revolutionized commercial air service. Lindbergh worked with Juan Trippe, Henry Ford, Amelia Earhart, Will Rogers and others to develop a number of airlines, including Pan American Airways and TWA. After his marriage to Anne Spencer Morrow in 1929, the internationally famous couple conducted scientific air explorations that led to the first transoceanic air passenger service. He and Anne had six children: Charles, Jr.; Jon; Land; Scott; Anne; and Reeve, between 1932 and 1945. The tragic kidnapping and murder of their son Charles, Jr., in 1932 was called "The Crime of the Century."
In the 1930s Lindbergh became a biomedical engineer with Dr. Alexis Carrel at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) and invented the perfusion pump, a prototype of the artificial heart, documented in their book, The Culture of Organs. To protect their son Jon from unwelcome press attention, the Lindberghs moved to England in 1935 and in 1938 to France to live near Carrel. At the request of the American Embassy in Germany Lindbergh made five trips from 1936 to 1938 to evaluate German air power for the United States State Department. The Lindbergh family returned to the United States in 1939. Before and after World War II, he served in the United States Air Force, but resigned to speak out against American intervention and joined the America First Committee in 1941. During the war Lindbergh served as technical consultant for the Ford Motor Company developing the B-24 bomber and for United Aircraft testing fighter planes. He also conducted air altitude flying tests at the Mayo Clinic using himself as a guinea pig and invented the "jump bottle," to provide oxygen to flyers when they lost consciousness. As a civilian advisor he flew fifty combat missions in the South Pacific in 1944.
After the war Lindbergh served on numerous government advisory committees concerned with aviation training, national security, and space exploration. In 1954 President Eisenhower promoted him to the rank of brigadier general stating that Lindbergh's work had significantly shortened the war in the Pacific by enabling pilots to reach many targets formerly beyond their range and thereby saving many lives. In the same year he was awarded the 1953 Pulitzer Prize for his autobiography The Spirit of St. Louis. Billy Wilder directed the movie version starring Jimmy Stewart released in 1957.
Thereafter Lindbergh dedicated himself to conservation causes as an officer and spokesman for the Nature Conservancy, the World Wildlife Fund, and other groups. He announced his growing concerns in a series of articles published in Reader's Digest, one of which included his most famous quote, "I realized that if I had to choose, I would rather have birds than airplanes." He was successful in persuading the Alaska legislature to alter the planned route of the oil pipeline to mitigate its impact on polar bear migration and some countries to limit their whale harvesting. In 1969 he was awarded the Bernard M. Baruch Conservation Prize for 1968. One of his last successful projects was to convince the United States government not to permit America to support supersonic air transportation. For the last thirty years of his life Lindbergh lived in Connecticut, with homes in Switzerland and in Hana, Maui, where he died of lymphoma in 1974. In 1978, his Autobiography of Values was published posthumously.
Anne Morrow Lindbergh (1906 Jun 22 - 2001 Feb 7), author and aviator, was born Anne Spencer Morrow in Englewood, New Jersey, the daughter of Dwight W. Morrow, an investment banker, diplomat, and United States senator and Elizabeth Reeve Cutter, an educator. She had three siblings, Elisabeth, Dwight, Jr., and Constance. She was educated at Miss Chapin's School and Smith College. During her senior year she was introduced to Charles Augustus Lindbergh in December 1927 at the American Embassy in Mexico City where her father was serving as ambassador. They were married in a secret ceremony in May 1929 at her parents' estate in Englewood, New Jersey. She wanted to become a professional aviator and undertook an intense study of flying, radio theory, Morse code, and navigation, earning a pilot's license and setting a transcontinental speed record with her husband in 1930 when she was seven months pregnant. Anne Lindbergh was the first woman in the United States to obtain a glider pilot's license
In July 1931, the Lindberghs took off on an extended survey flight for Pan American Airways over the Arctic Circle in Canada to Japan and China. After the tragic kidnapping and murder of her son Charles Jr., in 1932, she took some comfort in narrating her experiences as co-pilot and navigator in her first book, North to the Orient, published in 1935. The memoir went on to win the National Book Award and launch a celebrated career. After the birth of their second son, Jon, they undertook a second air survey expedition through the North Atlantic spending a happy period of time in Greenland where they mapped the mountain ranges and took air samples. They then flew south through Europe to Africa returning across the South Atlantic to Brazil and north to New York. In 1934, the National Geographic Society recognized her forty thousand miles of exploration with its prestigious Hubbard Award. She was the first woman to receive it.
To protect their son Jon from intrusive publicity, the Lindberghs moved to England in 1935 after the kidnapping and murder trial of Bruno Hauptmann. In 1938 they moved to France to be near her husband's scientific colleague Alexis Carrel. During those years she wrote about their Atlantic expedition, first for National Geographic and in a second best-selling book, Listen! The Wind, published in 1938. In The Wave of the Future (1940), a book-length essay, she tried to interpret their non-interventionist position to the public. During World War II she was kept busy raising four children: Jon, Land, Scott, and Anne. While Charles worked on bomber development at the Ford factory, Anne found some time to study sculpting at the Cranbrook Academy of Art. Her last child, Reeve, was born in 1945. From the late 1940s through the 1960s, Anne Lindbergh published a large number of articles and poems in literary, women's, and general magazines on a variety of personal and international issues. She wrote about the importance of balancing personal needs, social expectations, and obligations to family and community in her most popular and enduring work, Gift from the Sea (1955). Next to the Bible it was the non-fiction best seller of the year and sold 430,000 copies. To date, well over eight million copies have been sold, and at least 30,000 copies are sold annually.
Anne Morrow Lindbergh was motivated to write an essay, "The Heron and the Astronaut," after the Lindberghs attended the Apollo 8 launch from the Kennedy Space Center on December 21, 1968, the astronauts' first flight into the orbit of the moon. It was published in 1969 under the title Earth Shine, with her essay on Africa, "Immersion in Life." The Lindberghs built a modest home in Hana, Maui, Hawaii in 1969-1970. Working with the Nature Conservancy, Anne and Charles Lindbergh made substantial contributions toward the purchase of land in the Valley of the Seven Sacred Pools in Maui to extend Haleakala National Park more than 4000 acres from the inland crater to the ocean. After her husband's death in 1974, she devoted much of her time to editing and publishing five volumes of her diaries and letters covering her life through the end of World War II.
Anne Morrow Lindbergh was enshrined in the National Aviation Hall of Fame July 21, 1979, "for outstanding contributions to aviation by her participation in pioneering flights surveying air routes to the Orient and Europe, and as an extraordinary author encouraging public appreciation of aviation and air travel." In the 1990s she moved from her home in Connecticut to her daughter Reeve's family farm in Vermont. Reeve Lindbergh dealt with the last seventeen months of her mother's life in the book No More Words, a sensitive and loving memoir of their time together, published in 2001. In 2012, the fourteenth book of her writings was published, Against Wind and Tide: Letters and Journals, 1947-1986, based on her papers in Manuscripts and Archives.
Aeronautics; Transatlantic flights; World War, 1939-1945; Africa; Arctic regions; Asia; Germany; Latin America; Southwest, New; Photographs; Air pilots; Authors; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974; Cutter family; Lindbergh family; Morrow family; Spirit of St. Louis (Airplane)
- Charles Augustus Lindbergh, 1902-1974; Series I
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged as follows: portraits followed by all other photographs in the series filed chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes photographic prints and negatives that primarily depict Charles Augustus Lindbergh, individually and with others, including Anne Morrow Lindbergh, his parents, friends, and associates. Also included are photographs taken during the United States Southwest, Pacific and North Atlantic explorations. The bulk of the photographs date from 1902 to 1945 and document Charles Augustus Lindbergh's childhood; aviation career, including airmail service, barnstorming, and his historic transatlantic flight and subsequent expeditions in 1931, and 1933, with Anne Morrow Lindbergh; interest in him by the media; and his activities just prior to and during World War II, including his tours of Nazi Germany. Additional photographs document travels, interest in environmental conservation and contributions to the development of the airline industry. Many of the photographs from 1928 through the 1930s include Anne Morrow Lindbergh and document her relationship with Charles, contributions to aviation and the Southwest, Pacific, and North Atlantic expeditions. Researchers should note the following. Some of the captions on photographs from Lindbergh's youth identify him as "CAL, Jr.", however he was not a junior and did not refer to himself as such. Additionally, some of the photographs in the series do not depict Charles Augustus Lindbergh but are filed in the series in order to maintain groups of pictures belonging together intact.
  Photographs of Charles Augustus Lindbergh that are part of a group of family photographs are filed in Series III, Charles Augustus Lindbergh and Anne Morrow Lindbergh family. Oversized materials are filed in Oversize at the end of the collection.
  - Portraits, Circa 1902-1949 (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  - As infant, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - As infant, Circa 1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - With Charles Henry Land, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Duck hunting, Circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Playing with toy cannon and gun, Circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - With Charles August Lindbergh at Congress, Circa 1907 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - In Minnesota, Circa 1907-1912 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - In Washington, DC, Circa 1907-1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - At Belle Island and Lake Ruth, Minnesota, Circa 1908 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - With Spot (pet dog), Circa 1908-1910 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Negatives, Circa 1908-1911 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - With family at Cass Lake and Lake Ruth, Minnesota, Circa 1909 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - With Fluffy (pet cat), Circa 1909 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - With Mischief (pet cat) and her kittens, Circa 1909 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - At Arlington National Cemetery, Virginia, Circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - With Charles Henry Land, Circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - In Little Falls, Minnesota, Circa 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - At a zoo and in a park?, Circa 1911 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rolling Easter eggs at the White House, Washington, DC, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - On hunting trip with Charles August Lindbergh, Circa 1911 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - On a farm?, Circa 1911-1915 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Portraits with Charles August Lindbergh, Circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Feeding a chipmunk, Circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - On a family trip (album), 1913 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - On a raft, Circa 1913 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - With Dingo (pet dog), Circa 1913 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Portraits with Charles August Lindbergh, Circa 1913 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - At the May festival, Circa 1914 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - With family on Mississippi River trip, Circa 1915 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - In classroom, Washington, DC, Circa 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - On a farm, Circa 1916-1919 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - With a basket of sheep, Circa 1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - With Wagoosh (pet dog), 1918 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - In a canoe with friends, Circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - University of Wisconsin Rifle Club and Pistol Team, Circa 1920-1922 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - University of Wisconsin rush, Circa 1920-1922 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - University of Wisconsin dormitory, Circa 1921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - At Reserve Officer Training Corps, Circa 1921 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - At Camp Knox, Kentucky, 1921 June 16-July 20 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - On Excelsior motorcycle, 1921 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - In Florida, 1921 July-August (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - On a farm, 1921 September (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - In Madison, Wisconsin, 1921 November 20-1922 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - At flight training in Lincoln, Nebraska, 1922 July (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Airplane crash, Circa 1923 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - With Leon A. Klink and his Canuck, Circa 1923 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - With Lamb's ship (airplane), 1923 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - With his Jenny, Circa 1923 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - At Kelly Field and Brooks Field, Circa 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - In Pensacola, Florida, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Barnstorming, Circa 1925 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - With Dwight Whitney Morrow at Princeton University, Circa 1925 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Air Service Training, Circa 1925 January-April (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - At Lambert Field, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Air Service Commission, 1925 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Airplane crash and emergency jump, 1925 June 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Airmail flights, Circa 1926 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Images compiled by Warner Brothers research department, Circa 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    Photographs compiled from various sources probably for research for The Spirit of St. Louis film. Additional images marked with the Warner Brothers Research Department stamp are found thoughout the series.
  - The badger fight, 1926 March 13 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Airplane crash, 1926 Sep, November (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Garden party for Lindbergh, Circa 1927 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - General, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Passport photographs, Circa 1927 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Postcards of Charles Augustus Lindbergh, Circa 1927 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    From the United States, England, France and Germany.
  - In Germany with Louis Blériot, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - In suit and flight helmet, 1927 March (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - In plane and with navigation charts, 1927 April (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - At Lambert Field in St. Louis, Missouri, 1927 May 12 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - With the Spirit of St. Louis, 1927 May 13-20 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - With Byrd, Fonck, and Chamberlin, 1927 May 13-20 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - In flight pants, 1927 May 13-20 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - In the cockpit of the Spirit of St. Louis, 1927 May 13-20 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - With kitten, 1927 May 13-20 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Test flights, 1927 May 14-16 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Applying for passport, 1927 May 16 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - With Evangeline Lodge Land Lindbergh, 1927 May 16 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Autographed photograph, 1927 May 19 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General, 1927 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Fueling the Spirit of St. Louis, 1927 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - In flight suit, 1927 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Taking off in the Spirit of St. Louis from Roosevelt Field, New York, 1927 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - First hour of flight in the Spirit of St. Louis, 1927 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - With Ambassador Herrick in Paris, France, 1927 May 21-June 5 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - In Paris, France, 1927 May 21-22 (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - Receiving the Légion D'honneur, 1927 May 23 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - With Trubee Davison, 1927 May 23 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - At Le Bourget airport, 1927 May 24 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - At air display and with Raymond Orteig, 1927 May 24 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - At Hotel Ambassador, 1927 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Leaving France for Brussels, 1927 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Includes an aerial shot of airplane.
  - In Brussels, 1927 May 29 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - With Sir Alan Cobham, 1927 May 31 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - With the Prince of Wales, 1927 June 1 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - At Croydon and Buckingham Palace, 1927 June 4 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - On USS Memphis, 1927 June 10-11 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - In New York, New York, 1927 June 13 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - New York City parade, 1927 June 13 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - With Raymond Orteig, 1927 June 16 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - At Lambert Airport, 1927 June 17 (?) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - St. Louis parade, 1927 June 18 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
  - In Hartford, Connecticut, 1927 July 20 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    First stop on United States tour.
  - In Providence, Rhode Island, 1927 July 21 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - In Boston, Massachusetts, 1927 July 22 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - In Concord, New Hampshire, 1927 July 23 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - In Old Orchard Beach, Maine, 1927 July 25 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - In Rochester, New York, 1927 July 29 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - In Berea, Ohio, Circa 1927 August 1-6 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - In Columbus, Ohio, 1927 August 5 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - In Cincinnati, Ohio, 1927 August 6 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - In Indianapolis, Indiana, 1927 August 9-10 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - In Detroit, Michigan, at the Ford factory, 1927 August 11 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - In Kenosha, Wisconsin, 1927 August 20-23 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - At the air races in Cleveland, Ohio, 1927 August 24 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Parade, Minneapolis, Minnesota, 1927 August 24? (Box 6, Folder 22)